<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plans on Solus</title>
    <link>https://solus-project.com/categories/plans/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Plans on Solus</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 17:19:31 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://solus-project.com/categories/plans/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Replacement of Release Schedule</title>
      <link>https://solus-project.com/blog/replacement-of-release-schedule/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Jul 2016 17:19:31 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://solus-project.com/blog/replacement-of-release-schedule/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In the not so distant past, Solus followed a static point release model. Our most current release at this time is 1.2, with a 1.2.1 planned to drop in the near future.
However, we also recently &lt;a href=&#34;https://solus-project.com/posts/this-week-in-solus-31&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; our move to a rolling release model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, these two schools of thought are in contradiction of one another. Going forward, the old release schedule is &lt;strong&gt;officially&lt;/strong&gt;, entirely dropped, and the branching
pattern of a point-release-system is also shed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;important-points&#34;&gt;Important Points&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no longer a concept of separate major releases. You will always run on the current “distribution version”.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Support, therefore, does not end for the current, and only, series. Note however you are still expected to update your system. We’ll introduce some changes to make this
simpler to manage, of course.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no longer a concept of “1.3”, “2.0”, etc. Future ISOs will follow the internal versioning system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Future ISOs will land both features and package refreshes. Whilst you can always configure your installed Solus to match that of the ISO, through package selection, installer
features are only ever available in reinstalls (This is the only time you ever see the installer)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The internal versioning system at present is based on the concept of major releases, so it will therefore be dropped. For example, the 1.2 release is internally referred to
as: &lt;strong&gt;1.201629.7.0&lt;/strong&gt;. At minimum, we’ll drop the major version, and use this scheme in future ISO updates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-2-1-update&#34;&gt;1.2.1 - Update&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can only apologise in announcing that yes, 1.2.1 has been delayed. This has primarily come about due to a mixture of circumstances (work schedules), a wish to ensure consistency
and longevity in the installations (GNOME 3.20 updates), and the migration to a rolling release model. As soon as it is appropriate, 1.2.1 will be released. However, the release
schedule is now &lt;strong&gt;officially withdrawn&lt;/strong&gt;, leaving us some extra time to get 1.2.1 polished to the level we require.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;coming-items&#34;&gt;Coming Items&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our upcoming update list involves, but is not limited to:
- Update to GCC 6.1.0 (ongoing right now, handling libmpx incorporation)
- Move to GNOME 3.20.x
- Update to X.Org Server 1.18.4
- Ongoing rebuilds to utilise newly available CPU features on the build server to improve Solus packages
- Budgie 10.2.7 – whilst we initially envisaged going directly to 10.3, which has outstanding goals, we’ve opted to provide a maintenance release of Budgie to accommodate all Budgie
downstreams in the near future, due to the already extensive diff since 10.2.6. You can see the latest git build in the featured image for this post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;advantages&#34;&gt;Advantages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core advantage to the withdrawal of this static release schedule is that it in fact enables us to land features with a higher velocity, and &lt;strong&gt;maintain&lt;/strong&gt; that velocity over time. With
the move to a rolling release, one of our primary goals is in increasing the project cadence. As such, this frees us up to land future updates and refreshed ISOs, as and when new
features, fixes and changes are available, as opposed to being tied to a rigid schedule. In the long run, this will result in &lt;strong&gt;more&lt;/strong&gt; ISO releases and updates, enabling incremental testing
of technology in Solus.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This Week in Solus #32</title>
      <link>https://solus-project.com/blog/this-week-in-solus-install-32/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2016 10:28:31 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://solus-project.com/blog/this-week-in-solus-install-32/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the 32nd installation of This Week in Solus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;solus-1-2-1-releases-tomorrow&#34;&gt;Solus 1.2.1 Releases Tomorrow&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re really excited to be releasing our last “traditional” release, Solus 1.2.1, tomorrow. We opted to delay by a day just to ensure we don’t push ourselves too hard after the recent Hackfest, as well as being able to take the time to do additional QA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;infrastructure-improvements-closure-of-1-0-upgrade-path&#34;&gt;Infrastructure Improvements &amp;amp; Closure of 1.0 Upgrade Path&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have used Bugzilla since mid-2015 and while it has served us well, we are continuously reviewing alternatives and as of Friday, July 22nd, we will be &lt;strong&gt;locking down our BTS&lt;/strong&gt;. This will enable us to shift to a better alternative and cherry-pick bug history to migrate over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This downtime for the Bugzilla will also open the window for additional infrastructure maintenance and &lt;strong&gt;deprecate the upgrade path&lt;/strong&gt; from Solus 1.0, which was released over 6 months ago. This means that updating from 1.0 release &lt;strong&gt;will no longer be possible&lt;/strong&gt; after Friday and we will be removing the old repository. If you have already upgraded to 1.2, whether it be through the migration tooling during 1.1 or after, &lt;strong&gt;you will not be affected&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;impromptu-hackfest-sundays-with-solus&#34;&gt;Impromptu Hackfest &amp;amp; Sundays with Solus&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, we decided to have an impromptu hackfest to work on items for Solus 1.2.1. If you have the time to watch, we’d recommend it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div data-solus-component=&#34;video-player&#34;&gt;
	&lt;noscript&gt;
		We&#39;d love to be able to show you an awesome video.&lt;br /&gt;
		Mind enabling JavaScript please?
	&lt;/noscript&gt;
	&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/hZexPAobsSo?rel=0&#34;
		width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;395&#34;
		frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
		allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;
	&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;


&lt;p&gt;If you just want a summary of the impromptu Hackfest or want to hear what is coming up next week, check out our short Sundays with Solus!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div data-solus-component=&#34;video-player&#34;&gt;
	&lt;noscript&gt;
		We&#39;d love to be able to show you an awesome video.&lt;br /&gt;
		Mind enabling JavaScript please?
	&lt;/noscript&gt;
	&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/mePcwcdO66s?rel=0&#34;
		width=&#34;700&#34; height=&#34;395&#34;
		frameborder=&#34;0&#34;
		allowfullscreen=&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;
	&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>This Week in Solus #31</title>
      <link>https://solus-project.com/blog/this-week-in-solus-install-31/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2016 10:28:35 +0300</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://solus-project.com/blog/this-week-in-solus-install-31/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the 31st installation of This Week in Solus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;operation-go-moar-faster&#34;&gt;Operation Go Moar Faster&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solus has always held the philosophy of a “stable core, updated apps”. To achieve the level of stability we desire, we have been utilizing the LTS branch of the Linux kernel, prioritizing stability in our graphics stack, and sticking to a specific GNOME release series for each major release of Solus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be more precise, Solus 1.0 shipped with GNOME 3.18.x and the plan of using GNOME 3.22.x in Solus 2.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the “updated apps” portion of that philosophy, this has meant we have had the liberty of quickly delivering updates of applications outside of the GNOME stack to our users, e.g. Atom, Firefox, LibreOffice, Thunderbird, and so-forth without concern of a shift in the “core” of Solus and issues with stability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we are far from conservative even with the “core” of Solus. Before Mesa 12 was even released, we were using Mesa 12 RC4. We have shifted from gcc 4.8 to 5.3.0 in the lifetime of Solus. We ship the latest glibc (2.23). We even have plans on shifting to the latest Pulseaudio. The reality is a conservative operating system just doesn’t do these things. We’ve dealt head-on with a variety of changes to Solus, whether they be renames of the entire operating system (remember EvolveOS?), repo location changes, to shifting users from Solus 1.0 to 1.1 across a Python UCS4 migration. If there is one truth, one thing we have learned over the course of all this it is the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re really &lt;strong&gt;good&lt;/strong&gt; at keeping things &lt;strong&gt;stable&lt;/strong&gt; and really &lt;strong&gt;bad&lt;/strong&gt; at &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; being a rolling release. So effective immediately, &lt;strong&gt;Solus now follows a rolling release model&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://solus-project.com/imgs/autobots-rollout.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Autobots, roll out.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does this mean for you? We’re taking it up a notch from just updated apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We’ll be updating to Pulseaudio 9 to resolve issues regarding sound playback over HDMI, likely making that into Solus 1.2.1.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Next week after Solus 1.2.1, we’re rolling out GNOME 3.20. Thanks to work done by horst3180, Budgie is already compatible with GNOME 3.20, so that will not be a blocker for updating the GNOME stack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So long as you keep your system updated, your Solus 1.x installation will be supported indefinitely. Releases are primarily for us to focus on milestones and provide a snapshot for installation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://solus-project.com/imgs/magic.gif&#34; alt=&#34;Magic.&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;ypkg-improvements&#34;&gt;YPKG Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ikey has landed a multitude of improvements to ypkg recently, including:
- Support for using git as a source!
- Automatic dependencies when using a git source or for emul32 builds. No more needing to add glibc-32bit-devel, libgcc-32bit, and libstdc++-32bit as builddeps when you have emul32 enabled.
- Enabling + and . (period) within package names.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>